<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>GM - 2012</title><link>https://gm.lv/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 13:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>PHP error handling</title><link>https://gm.lv/php-error-handling-en.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;You can learn new stuff each day, for example we have just recently turned php errors into exceptions. It is so good, that I decided even to write about it here. Currently we do this only on development environment for safety, because the page code is quite old. Anyways, every php development should do this to get rid of php's annoying error reporting and hopefully make a better product. So enough talking, here is the code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/3790196"&gt;https://gist.github.com/3790196&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gints Murāns</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2012 13:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:gm.lv,2012-09-26:/php-error-handling-en.html</guid><category>Sākums</category><category>2012</category></item><item><title>PHP/Code Editors</title><link>https://gm.lv/phpcode-editors-en.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In general I need two main features from the code editor. (I will not talk about obvious ones like unicode and unix/win/osx line ending support, fast, good UI, etc) And those are: sftp browser and just a good editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody seems to ever get it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TextMate seems to be fast, but lacks sftp support. Same for sublime (which is also just weird editor). Same for Kod. Same for lots of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are editors with bunch of features, but are so terribly slow or lacks design so much or just can't seem to get some of the features right. For example eclipse and all its crazy movement. Or komodo with its seems-to-be-unfinished sftp panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are few those that shine out like Espresso and Coda. They are not bad at all, but for example Espresso is kind of slow on my computer and I can't get used to its sftp browser. On the other hand Coda is nicely made and is full of features, but I don't really use them all so from my point …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gints Murāns</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2012 03:59:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:gm.lv,2012-05-02:/phpcode-editors-en.html</guid><category>Sākums</category><category>2012</category></item></channel></rss>