<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>GM</title><link href="http://gm.lv/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://gm.lv/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://gm.lv/en/</id><updated>2019-05-03T16:02:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>Another PUBG issue</title><link href="http://gm.lv/en/another-pubg-issue.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-05-03T16:02:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-05-03T16:02:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2019-05-03:/en/another-pubg-issue.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Update (2020-02-03): Brought some things up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been "whining" on reddit about pubg issues for a while now, ~~and I think I finally figured it out.~~ - to be honest pubg is a weird game. I have been playing lot of COD:MW lately and some CS:GO too, and sometimes I win, sometimes I lose there, as it should be cosidering that I am quite average gamer here. But PUBG is an annoying nightmare, nothing works for me, I lose 95% of time even if its not an RNG case. Anyway the following is still relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take a look at my &lt;a href="http://gm.lv/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html"&gt;other post&lt;/a&gt; on how to get a better performance in Pubg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lets start from the beginning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together a computer just for gaming around a year ago. At the time x299 chipset just came out and I thought - the newer, the better, so I bought Aorus Gaming 3, X299 + i5-7640x + HyperX FURY DDR4-2133 with some generic (shitty) PSU, RX550 GPU, generic mouse and keyboard, SSD, and upgraded stock cooler to a better one from Cooler …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Update (2020-02-03): Brought some things up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been "whining" on reddit about pubg issues for a while now, ~~and I think I finally figured it out.~~ - to be honest pubg is a weird game. I have been playing lot of COD:MW lately and some CS:GO too, and sometimes I win, sometimes I lose there, as it should be cosidering that I am quite average gamer here. But PUBG is an annoying nightmare, nothing works for me, I lose 95% of time even if its not an RNG case. Anyway the following is still relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take a look at my &lt;a href="http://gm.lv/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html"&gt;other post&lt;/a&gt; on how to get a better performance in Pubg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lets start from the beginning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together a computer just for gaming around a year ago. At the time x299 chipset just came out and I thought - the newer, the better, so I bought Aorus Gaming 3, X299 + i5-7640x + HyperX FURY DDR4-2133 with some generic (shitty) PSU, RX550 GPU, generic mouse and keyboard, SSD, and upgraded stock cooler to a better one from Cooler Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First - the GPU - RX550 just couldn't handle anything more than CS GO, so after a while I got a chance to upgrade to a used 980ti and later got 1080 ti for free (nice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While other games were fine, Pubg was not, I was constantly loosing, so I thought it must be something in the hardware and kept upgrading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started with the mouse and keyboard to ones from Steelseries - I am very happy with those. Next, PSU to corsair rm750x, because I was seeing some strange voltage drops in HWMonitor and, as the generic one once was on fumes (I know :)), I thought thats probably the case why I get stutterings. It wasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gave my ram away to a friend and upgraded to Crucial Ballistix Tactical DDR4-2666 - this actually improved framerates, but not the stuttering/delayed action feeling. Later on had a chance to upgrade to m.2 drive, which improved loading times, but not much more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I thought about upgrading CPU, because clearly i5 was bottlenecking the GPU, but figured to start with OC'ing the i5. Before that I knew that current cooler is not gonna handle it, so that was upgraded to Corsair H115i PRO AIO cooler. Currently I am running i5-7640x at 5Ghz without any problems, only just upgraded one of the stock fan on H115i to Noctua nf-a14 industrialppc-2000, because temperatures sometimes went over 80 degrees. It is quite a lot louder, but thats ok. Did this solve stuttering / delayed action feeling - no, although pubg fps is now around 180 - 240fps, which is very good for pubg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now the best part.&lt;/strong&gt; I had a 100Mbit optical internet from my provider and at some point I upgraded it to 250Mbit. One evening we were playing pubg and a friend of mine had already lost the game, was spectating me, while waiting. And he says something like: "He got you!". And when he was at the "He" part of the sentence, only then I saw, that I died in the game. Then I thought - &lt;strong&gt;how the hell he saw that before me?&lt;/strong&gt; So I went investigating over google (again) and found out something called bufferbloat. It turns out, over very fast networks, network devices does a lot of data buffering, which can cause latency issues in realtime applications like fast paced games. So I searched for a network bufferbloat tester thing and found &lt;a href="http://www.dslreports.com/speedtest"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt; which additionally to speedtest, also tests for a bufferbloat. My router has this thing called QOS, where I can setup manual speed limit for a network device, so I did that. Tested speedtest from dslreports against various speed limits and found out that 50Mbit was the best one with A+ bufferbloat rating. Then I tried playing the game and it was like a night versus day kind of thing. Now I finally can pickup items while running, and I wouldn't die before seeing my opponents, etc. So this is after all those upgrades and 600+ hours on Pubg thinking I am so bad at this gaming stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I had a suspicion that something is not ok with .. well .. something, it was so torturing thinking that I just suck at pubg, but still having this suspicion of something else to blame for that delayed action. Also I think my CSGO gameplay has improved a bit after this. So far Fornite seems to have the best impact of them all - I can finally land those shots, also far away ones, unlike before 85% (I am guessing here, but it was really bad) of all the shots would be missing the target. Haven't had a chance to play much of Apex, to tell anything about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thats it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Too fast internet was causing delays while playing online fps games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="Games"></category><category term="Pubg"></category></entry><entry><title>Ultimate guide to solve PUBG stuttering issues</title><link href="http://gm.lv/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-20T17:46:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-11-20T17:46:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2018-11-20:/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Update (2020-02-03): Brought some things up to date.
Update (2019-05-03): Few typo and speeling fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have been fighting with fps drops and stuttering issues for quite a while now, and I have a decent system. Here is what I have found. This guide is for nvidia with a better GPU than CPU (apparently that stuff matters), and most probably won't work for everyone, but you can find ideas to increase performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid hdd, go for ssd or even better M.2 NMVE drive. Last one loads games, and system it self, million times faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for performance middle ground. For example, download OpenHardwareMonitor, check that CPU and GPU utilisation is somewhat consistent. Later on that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have a decent mouse and keyboard, especially mouse. ~~Upgrading generic mouse to SteelSeries Rival was like a day versus night for me.~~ Switched to Logitech G305 and don't want to ever look back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is an option for you, go for a 144Hz monitor. Even if your computer can handle only 90fps, its still a lot better than 60Hz …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Update (2020-02-03): Brought some things up to date.
Update (2019-05-03): Few typo and speeling fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have been fighting with fps drops and stuttering issues for quite a while now, and I have a decent system. Here is what I have found. This guide is for nvidia with a better GPU than CPU (apparently that stuff matters), and most probably won't work for everyone, but you can find ideas to increase performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid hdd, go for ssd or even better M.2 NMVE drive. Last one loads games, and system it self, million times faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for performance middle ground. For example, download OpenHardwareMonitor, check that CPU and GPU utilisation is somewhat consistent. Later on that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have a decent mouse and keyboard, especially mouse. ~~Upgrading generic mouse to SteelSeries Rival was like a day versus night for me.~~ Switched to Logitech G305 and don't want to ever look back.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is an option for you, go for a 144Hz monitor. Even if your computer can handle only 90fps, its still a lot better than 60Hz. Also if your PC can handle it, just go to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OX31kZbAXsA"&gt;240fps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn off the G-Sync and V-Sync, it does make the game to look quite a bit smoother, but if you want maximum performance, I suggest turning it off. Also Fast sync may improve the looks but performance is somewhat limited. Yes I know its just 1 frame difference, but we are aiming for performance here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Always use Fullscreen mode, without windows. It drains CPU a LOT.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup page file. Here is one example how to do it: &lt;a href="https://www.geeksinphoenix.com/blog/post/2016/05/10/how-to-manage-windows-10-virtual-memory.aspx"&gt;Page File Setup&lt;/a&gt;. Set same Initial size and Maximum size. If you have 4GB - don't play this game. If you have 8GB, set it to 4069 - no point setting it any larger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure your power settings are set to Maximum performance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Also make sure you set texture filtering in nvidia control panel to performance, it will look worse, but as it turns out this greatly impacts fps drops and stuttering when tested 1% and 0.1% fps low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usually you would think the bigger is better, but, as it turns out, thats not the case with mouse and keyboard polling rates. Decreasing polling rate from 1000hz to 500hz (I did it on both - mouse and keyboard) seems to be the single most effective way that reduced lagging feeling for me. I think what is happening here is that when a mouse is constantly sending movement updates at 1kHz, my cpu (or game?) couldn't handle it, thats why when I was clicking mouse buttons, they always felt like a bit delayed. At first I thought it is monitor being at 60Hz. After getting 144Hz monitor, I thought it is cpu, that cannot handle video processing. After smoothing fps out, I thought its nvidia settings. After tweaking those, I thought it is a buggy ssd, after upgrading ssd to m.2 it actually seemed better. Who knows. Then somebody on reddit suggested to look into mouse polling rate, and turns out that was the issue. Before this change I had set fps limit to 94, but in-game it was around 88-90. After changing polling rate it is now quite steady at 94. &lt;strong&gt;This only applies if you have weaker or older CPU&lt;/strong&gt; - I have since then bought a new cpu and it is working same on both 500hz and 1000hz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPU vs CPU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a big one. If you have a good GPU, but not so good CPU, and no limit on fps and graphics settings on the low side, you will notice stuttering, lagging, ping drops, etc. Thats because GPU says: I'm ready, give me more, but CPU cannot give more, because it is at 100%. If thats the case, you should either lower fps or give more work to the GPU, so it cannot handle so many frames. I went the first way and found that my CPU can handle 94fps, leaving room for system it self (background processes, networking, etc). Maybe it could do a bit more, but don't think I would gain much more with this cpu.
If you cannot get stable 60fps, most probably kills are gonna be hard to get. Sneaking around is still an option, though. :D
To figure out what CPU I would need I used this &lt;a href="https://pc-builds.com/calculator/"&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;. ~~But it looks like its not working at the moment.~~&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NVidia Settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click second mouse button on Desktop -&amp;gt; NVIDIA Control Panel -&amp;gt; Manage 3d Settings.
Global settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="GlobalSettings" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/nvidia-global-settings.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pubg specific settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PubgSettings" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/nvidia-pubg-settings.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One thing to mention, I am setting preferred refresh rate &amp;amp; maximum pre-rendered frames (suggested is to set it to 1) to application controlled, so it self figures out what it needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;G-Sync off&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="GSync" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/nvidia-gsync.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Refresh Rate&lt;/strong&gt;
If your screen feels like 60hz, but you have a monitor that can do more, make sure its correctly set in nvidia settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="RefreshRate" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/nvidia-refresh-rate.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In-Game settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="InGame" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/in-game-settings.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AA - High caused a bit more fps drops, so I went with Medium. I wouldn't set it to Low, because it starts to look bad below Medium&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PP - Same as AA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shadows - Always Very Low&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Textures - Ultra puts more stress on GPU than on CPU. I'm not sure, but I guess choosing anything below Ultra does some scaling or additional loading or something that puts more strain on CPU.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Effects - No need for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Foliage - Same&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;View distance - this is interesting one. It seems to put more stress on cpu, but setting it to low causes weird rendering when zooming - stuff is appearing when you scope, and gets lost when not scoping. Thats why I am choosing Medium here for it to be not so noticeable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You don't need rest of the settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Hardware Monitor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="OHWM" src="http://gm.lv/en/images/pubg/open-hw-monitor.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update settings until you get somewhat consistent GPU and CPU utilisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Games"></category><category term="Games"></category><category term="Pubg"></category></entry></feed>