<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>GM - Games</title><link>http://gm.lv/en/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 16:02:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>Another Pubg guide</title><link>http://gm.lv/en/another-pubg-guide.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I have been "whining" on reddit about pubg issues for a while now, and I think I finally figured it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take a look at my &lt;a href="http://gm.lv/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html"&gt;other post&lt;/a&gt; on how to get a better performance in Pubg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lets start from the beginning?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put together a computer just for gaming around a year ago. At the time x299 chipset just came out and I thought - the newer, the better, so I bought Aorus Gaming 3, X299 + i5-7640x + HyperX FURY DDR4-2133 with some generic (shitty) PSU, RX550 GPU, generic mouse and keyboard, SSD, and upgraded stock cooler to a better one from Cooler Master.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First - the GPU - RX550 just couldn't handle anything more than CS GO, so after a while I got a chance to upgrade to a used 980ti and later got 1080 ti for free (nice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While other games were fine, Pubg was not, I was constantly loosing, so I thought it must be something in the hardware and kept upgrading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started with the mouse and keyboard to ones from Steelseries - I am very happy with those. Next, PSU …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gints Murāns</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 16:02:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:gm.lv,2019-05-03:/en/another-pubg-guide.html</guid><category>Games</category><category>Pubg</category></item><item><title>Ultimate guide to solve PUBG stuttering issues</title><link>http://gm.lv/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Update (2019-05-03): Few typo and speeling fixes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have been fighting with fps drops and stuttering issues for quite a while now, and I have a decent system. Here is what I have found. This guide is for nvidia with a better GPU than CPU (apparently that stuff matters), and most probably won't work for everyone, but you can find ideas to increase performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid hdd, go for ssd or even better M.2 NMVE drive. Last one loads games, and system it self, million times faster.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go for performance middle ground. For example, download OpenHardwareMonitor, check that CPU and GPU utilisation is somewhat consistent. Later on that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure you have a decent mouse and keyboard, especially mouse. Upgrading generic mouse to SteelSeries Rival was like a day versus night for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If it is an option for you, go for a 144Hz monitor. Even if your computer can handle only 90fps, its still a lot better than 60Hz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turn off the G-Sync and V-Sync, it does make the game to look quite a bit smoother, but if …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Gints Murāns</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2018 17:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:gm.lv,2018-11-20:/en/ultimate-guide-to-solve-pubg-stuttering-issues.html</guid><category>Games</category><category>Pubg</category></item></channel></rss>