<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>GM - 2009</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://gm.lv/feeds/tags_2009.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://gm.lv/en/</id><updated>2009-04-28T18:22:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>Opera</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/opera.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-04-28T18:22:00+03:00</published><updated>2009-04-28T18:22:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-04-28:/en/opera.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I accidentally visited &lt;a href="http://opera.com"&gt;http://opera.com&lt;/a&gt; , this is what i got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/04/picture-3-300x187.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Choices</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/choices.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-04-05T22:10:00+03:00</published><updated>2009-04-05T22:10:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-04-05:/en/choices.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are good choices and bad choices and you have to figure it out!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>A lot of "against" lately</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/a-lot-of-against-lately.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-03-20T07:21:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-03-20T07:21:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-03-20:/en/a-lot-of-against-lately.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;And here is another one. :) This time I am against Internet Explorer 6. Inspiration came after reading this &lt;a href="http://ra-ajax.org/how-to-join-the-war-against-ie6-on-your-own-websites.blog"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; . I think we all should follow Norway in this one, so I made a little html + css script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put that little source on your page and result will be similar to the one in picture, what is in Latvian, but below is download link to English version, too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/against-ie6.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download source: &lt;a href="/files/ie6-en.zip"&gt;en&lt;/a&gt;  | &lt;a href="/files/ie6-lv.zip"&gt;lv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Little comparison</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/little-comparison.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-03-16T19:28:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-03-16T19:28:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-03-16:/en/little-comparison.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday i wrote a little comparison test. Let an image show you the rest.more&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/ptest.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strange thing is that first time running php, it was a lot slower than ruby, bet still faster than java. And what for "Scala" - I put it here because I read that some part of twitter are using it. It is so slow when comparing to others so I saw no point to include it in &lt;em&gt;files&lt;/em&gt; test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/ptest.zip"&gt;Here are all files needed to make the test.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Microsoft</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/microsoft.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-03-16T03:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-03-16T03:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-03-16:/en/microsoft.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I hate Microsoft, really. Lets start from begining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last thursday a friend of mine asked me a question: "Is it possible to get Microsoft dynamics crm working with php? Send messages, etc.". I thought: "Never heard of it, but how hard it could be?" So I said, that I will look more into it that evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com/eu/"&gt;parallels&lt;/a&gt; , because I wanted to do some other tasks, also and because of windows 7 beta installation on bootcamp disk. So I got parallels and installed xp. That went really nice and easy. I spent a little time enjoying parallels "Coherence" mode and started to look farther. I was already downloaded MSCRM server and Client (at this point I smelt something bad is coming, because of client and server installations).more&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand that crm is working very closely with MS Outlook and MSSQL, so I installed MS Office and went to microsoft.com for mssql. I found MSSQL Express, which is for free, actually. After installing mssql I mounted crm server iso file and started installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly I was introduced …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I hate Microsoft, really. Lets start from begining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last thursday a friend of mine asked me a question: "Is it possible to get Microsoft dynamics crm working with php? Send messages, etc.". I thought: "Never heard of it, but how hard it could be?" So I said, that I will look more into it that evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started with &lt;a href="http://www.parallels.com/eu/"&gt;parallels&lt;/a&gt; , because I wanted to do some other tasks, also and because of windows 7 beta installation on bootcamp disk. So I got parallels and installed xp. That went really nice and easy. I spent a little time enjoying parallels "Coherence" mode and started to look farther. I was already downloaded MSCRM server and Client (at this point I smelt something bad is coming, because of client and server installations).more&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand that crm is working very closely with MS Outlook and MSSQL, so I installed MS Office and went to microsoft.com for mssql. I found MSSQL Express, which is for free, actually. After installing mssql I mounted crm server iso file and started installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly I was introduced with a lot of "Required components". Ok, that is not so bad, press install and everything gets installed. After some time of waiting and "reboot required", but ignored and error dialog popping up, comes next step. I filled organization name, next, next, next and then error dialog: "IIS is not installed". That made me wonder, but ok, there is checkbox "Create a new Web site", next. Then appeared "Select SQL Server" page. Crm server setup didn't find it, so I just put in localhost and pressed "next". There was something about "reporting services", wtf? Ok, "next". And here came a joy. It asked me for "Organizational unit". I have heard that word set before, but I didn't want to agree with myself. So I pressed the button - "Browse" and got a message: "Unable to browse for &lt;strong&gt;Active Directory&lt;/strong&gt; object". That wasn't so good, anymore.
Next I opened up google and searched for something like this: "active directory windows xp" and got back site, where somebody has wrote something like this: "You can't get Active Directory on windows xp". I already knew it, even before pressing that "Browse" button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thinking to myself: "OK!", and searched for windows server. First result was directing to microsoft web site, where I could download windows server beta version, so I did it. it was quite fast, installed, did it all again. Then something I don't remember, was not happy with windows 2008 server beta, this is where I started to become angry. "Ok, fine, fine." I searched again, downloaded windows 2003 server edition. This was not so fast any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I had windows 2003 server iso file, now. Ok, I opened parallels, "New Virtual Machine", "next", "next", some configuration and done. Fresh windows 2003 server was installed and didn't let me to download a file from microsoft web site, because of security. After I somehow manage to get that file I installed MS Office and MSSQL 2008 express. Went to google, searched how to install Active Directory, even created one user in it. Then I mounted Microsoft dynamics CRM server, "install", "next", "next", "error dialog", "next", "next", "Browse". It shows up as neded, "ok", "next". Stop!! "Microsoft exchange", "WTF???" This is where I got really angry, but i told to myself: "there is no need for a panic!". Google: "install exchange server" -&amp;gt; downloaded exchange server, installed and there was some requirements in process, too, for example SMTP server, what is hidden somewhere in "Add/Remove windows components". Finally, reboot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mount MSCRM, "install", "next", "next". "Next" after "Exchange server" page - everything is ok. Setup was checking installation, here we go again. It told me, that something is wrong with database. I changed passwords, I changed service users and passwords, I was going mad, when I wrote a query for google: "microsoft dynamics crm 3 mssql 2008 express" and found link, where somebody wrote something similar to this: "in order to install microsoft crm you will need to get enterprise or standard version of mssql". At this point I understood: "that is microsoft, there is no point of being mad, just go, search for mssql 2005 enterprise, download it .. install and that's it". So I did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presuming that I had already installed mssql (too lazy to write those "next", "error", "next"), I was at last page of crm installation and everything was fine, so I pressed "install" button and after that "close" button. Then I was sitting in my chair and asking myself: "So that's it? It really went without any errors?" (with sarcasm, of course)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next thing was, that I have to somehow connect to crm to actually do something with it. Somewhere between all those installations I found out, that it has soap module, server or whatever you call it. I just needed to find what url I have to connect. And you may guess, that it wasn't an easy step, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing I came accross, was msdn web site, there is something like documentation. So I walked around a little bit, found nothing and went to google, of course. :) Google said, that there is url like this: "http://localhost:5555/MSCRMservices/2006/crmservice.asmx", I opened it in Safari, it was asking for username and password. I entered tht usernames login information I created earlier, guess - it won't work. Aah.. After some searhing around I found out, that I need to add my users to CRM (or Exchange) server. So I did it and tried again, it worked. I got the page, with some little information about possible commands to the server. Of course it wasn't quite that I was looking for. So I googled again. I came accross link - "http://10.211.55.5:5555/MSCRMservices/2006/crmservice.asmx?wsdl" and, yes, it was soap connector, finally. But that is where the funniest part starts. Microsoft uses their authentication method called NTLM and, of course, there is no support for in-built soap client. Ok, there was some .. exactly one example in several web sites, what isn't working quite as well as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some looking around I went over php based library &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/nusoap/"&gt;nusoap&lt;/a&gt; . Nusoap have NTLM support. "Yes!" - I thought to myself. What's next? I have to find how to communicate with ms soap server. And you know, it is not so easy as it sounds. There are plenty of examples around, but they all are hand made xml, but I have nusoap class, what does it self. I just have to put right values in right places. And that is not so easy either. It started here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;went here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and ended here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What should I put in all those method arguments? Searched all over google, no example, nothing, just stupid msdn documentation web site with class reference, what is totally useless, if I don't know how to use it. So that was it. I started to think about other solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One I came up with was, that I could include mscrm in-built web client into iframe and all done, but as always it is not that simple. Firstly because users will have to enter their username and password again, and that is not worse thing. The even worse thing that in-built web client works only and only on microsoft internet explorer. So I asked myself: "What is that? CRM? It should be useful, not painful".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iframe solution didn't worked out, so I thought I could just make some php wrapper/proxy for that web client so users have just one limitation on browsers. I got it working with curl, but not quite working. I got through html code, what wasn't working either way. That was the moment I stopped doing anything and right after that opened parallels virtual machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I searched through all start menu items and didn't find anything that would be useable for mssql database browsing. I went to google, again. Searched for some tool. Google pointed me to microsoft web site. There is a tool named "Microsoft SQL web data administrator". I downloaded it, installed, launched, pressed start button. Internet explorer opened automatically to local address what gave me out and error. "F#!@@£% microsoft..".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went through all menu items searching for something that would be useable to change some permissions stuff in mssql. Nothing. Aaagh... I opened google for the last time, searched something, got answer that I need some "mssql studio.." thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only thing that came into my mind was - "Ok, that's it. I'm done here."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'm sitting in my chair and thinking: "How microsoft manage to get people to use their really stupid setups? Really, how?"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On ubuntu server edition this all would take me like half an hour job? I mean:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.sugarforge.org/frs/download.php/5087/SugarCE-5.2.0a.zip"&gt;http://www.sugarforge.org/frs/download.php/5087/SugarCE-5.2.0a.zip&lt;/a&gt;
unzip SugarCE-5.2.0a.zip
rm SugarCE-5.2.0a.zip
rm -R /var/www/&lt;em&gt;
mv -R ./SugarCE-5.2.0a/&lt;/em&gt; /var/www/
+ some little configuration and my crm website is ready to use. What about integration into another site. &lt;a href="http://www.sugarcrm.com/wiki/index.php?title=SOAP_Documentation"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt;  looks much better, than &lt;a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa683647.aspx"&gt;msdn&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Swedbank internet bank</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/swedbank-internet-bank.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-03-02T18:12:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-03-02T18:12:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-03-02:/en/swedbank-internet-bank.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Little thing, but still why there is button - "Hide accounts", what is totally useless, because it is only real thing in first page after login and only one I expect to be there. And, if we are getting into details, why there is no button for hiding ads? :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/03/ib-swedbank-lv-001-300x187.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Passed the test</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/passed-the-test.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-26T14:37:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-26T14:37:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-26:/en/passed-the-test.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot" src="http://trainhorns.net/sound/img/passed.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Created by &lt;a href="http://trainhorns.net"&gt;Train Horns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>A lot to say</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/a-lot-to-say.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-14T01:09:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-14T01:09:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-14:/en/a-lot-to-say.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to say, I just don't know how to. Or maybe I don't know how to summarize. The right words is just not coming out. When I write long posts at some point all post seems brainless. So I keep posting short posts. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>www.twestival.fm</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/wwwtwestivalfm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-14T00:56:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-14T00:56:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-14:/en/wwwtwestivalfm.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found about &lt;a href="http://twestival.com/"&gt;Twestival&lt;/a&gt;  some days ago somewhere on twitter. Today I saw already opened tab and looked more deeper into the site. I have watched videos on the site and now I'm looking through these &lt;a href="http://www.charitywater.org/projects/fromthefield/car.htm"&gt;pictures&lt;/a&gt;  and listening to this &lt;a href="http://www.twestival.fm/?p=93"&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;  (what is actually quite good). Interesting...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p.s. This &lt;a href="http://www.charitywater.org/about/scotts_story.htm"&gt;story&lt;/a&gt;  is even more interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>This is the good one</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/this-is-the-good-one.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-12T03:20:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-12T03:20:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-12:/en/this-is-the-good-one.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EhqZ0RU95d4"&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>First video on youtube</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/first-video-on-youtube.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-07T08:28:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-07T08:28:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-07:/en/first-video-on-youtube.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Video about our little buddy:
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jCZkYT7-pro"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jCZkYT7-pro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Skype status message from itunes</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/skype-status-message-from-itunes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-02-02T10:54:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-02-02T10:54:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-02-02:/en/skype-status-message-from-itunes.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was searching how to get "now playing" status from itunes to show in skype. Then I did not find anything. Today I remembered it and decided to try search again. I found nothing and with nothing I mean I couldn't find any application that could do that. But instead I found this forum post - &lt;a href="http://forum.skype.com/index.php?showtopic=83508"&gt;http://forum.skype.com/index.php?showtopic=83508&lt;/a&gt;  what made me wonder. So I looked in Skype settings and there it is - Cmd+, -&amp;gt; Advanced tab -&amp;gt; "Show iTunes song in my mood message". Simple enough. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p.s. I don't know if this works on windows skype too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>August rush</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/august-rush.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-31T02:25:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-31T02:25:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-31:/en/august-rush.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Just watched the movie .. again. You have to listen this song - &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ClnfSJuR26o"&gt;John Legend - Someday&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway the movie is heartwarming, even wathcing it second time.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Ill, updated</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/ill-updated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-20T10:36:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-20T10:36:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-20:/en/ill-updated.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm ill. 38.2 C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;She&lt;/strong&gt; is ill too :( - 39.1 C&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;p.s. I don't quite remember when last time I was ill like this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Salaries</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/salaries.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-16T07:15:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-16T07:15:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-16:/en/salaries.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;How can it be, that goverment is cutting off salaries for every unit, but leaving their self salaries as they were? So imagine preschool teacher, who have and had salary something about 250 ls after taxes and they had some bonuses. Now they don't. And now imagine some fat guy sitting in our government and getting salary something about 4000 ls more or less and without any wish to lower they incoms. They are threating us like an idiots. I do understand that there is crisis out there and we need to lower our expanses, but how can they cut off teacher salaries, what has always been to low and leave their unchanged. From what I have heared, they will talk about to cutt off their bonuses or not. :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how can we live in the country like this, when there is such a lot absurd and wories about tomorrow?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Wordpress updated</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/wordpress-updated.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-15T22:57:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-15T22:57:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-15:/en/wordpress-updated.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Little late, but I just updated my wordpress version to 2.7 and it looks great. Admin interface has got a lot of attention. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Windows 7</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/windows-7.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-15T22:44:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-15T22:44:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-15:/en/windows-7.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just installed windows 7 on my .. yes .. macbook. :) Everything went fine, without any problems, except install time, of course. :) But I guess it was fast comparing to Vista. First impression is very good, I mean really very good. Bad thing is that I don't remember my network key for wireless access point so I don't know if it is a windows problem or what. I tried to open "Explorer", "Internet explorer" and "media player" and they were doing quite fast. I know, there is no reason why to move back to windows, but I'm quite impressed about it, firstly because it looks beautiful, secondly, because it is fast even on laptop. But (always have some:) windows xp is fast too with fresh install. After some months it is/was always starting to drive me crazy. And another thing I have noticed - better computer, faster it gets slow.
So .. hard to say if it is fast or slow in real life - I will not use it in everyday basis (OS X has bought me:), but I would be lucky if …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just installed windows 7 on my .. yes .. macbook. :) Everything went fine, without any problems, except install time, of course. :) But I guess it was fast comparing to Vista. First impression is very good, I mean really very good. Bad thing is that I don't remember my network key for wireless access point so I don't know if it is a windows problem or what. I tried to open "Explorer", "Internet explorer" and "media player" and they were doing quite fast. I know, there is no reason why to move back to windows, but I'm quite impressed about it, firstly because it looks beautiful, secondly, because it is fast even on laptop. But (always have some:) windows xp is fast too with fresh install. After some months it is/was always starting to drive me crazy. And another thing I have noticed - better computer, faster it gets slow.
So .. hard to say if it is fast or slow in real life - I will not use it in everyday basis (OS X has bought me:), but I would be lucky if I could have need for using it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Returning references</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/returning-references.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-14T13:18:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-14T13:18:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-14:/en/returning-references.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is this working:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and this is not:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;showing me an error: Only variable references should be returned by reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess php compiler is not so smart to check if booth those return values in second example are variables.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Snowing</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/snowing.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-07T15:53:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-07T15:53:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-07:/en/snowing.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Great day, a lot of snow, everything white and peaceful and what is strange - it is not cold outside. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some fast images:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="s1" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5701-300x199.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="s2" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5692-300x199.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="s3" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5692.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="s4" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5691-300x199.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="s5" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5691.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img alt="s6" src="http://mstuff.org/blog/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/img_5711-300x199.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Framework</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/framework.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-07T08:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-07T08:01:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-07:/en/framework.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lately I have been writing some stuff about framework. So this post is to be little more insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before helplatvia.lv I was using codeigniter. But there are some things I don't like in it. I tought it could be good experience with open source products and decided to work on my own framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Written for php 5 and will not support php 4;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses PDO (php data objects) for making database queries so hopefully framework could use any database type PDO provides, you can find those &lt;a href="http://lv.php.net/manual/en/pdo.drivers.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; . Although there is some annoying things about pdo. For example, you cannot count on PDOStatement-&amp;gt;rowCount method, because it works only on affected rows, not selected. Some of the database types can return row count number on select too, but you can't truly be sure, if you admit that in some point you could change database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System is built on static classes, so you can access for example router class from everywhere. I can't find reason why you should initialize router class twice. Anyway you can choose your …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lately I have been writing some stuff about framework. So this post is to be little more insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before helplatvia.lv I was using codeigniter. But there are some things I don't like in it. I tought it could be good experience with open source products and decided to work on my own framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Written for php 5 and will not support php 4;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses PDO (php data objects) for making database queries so hopefully framework could use any database type PDO provides, you can find those &lt;a href="http://lv.php.net/manual/en/pdo.drivers.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; . Although there is some annoying things about pdo. For example, you cannot count on PDOStatement-&amp;gt;rowCount method, because it works only on affected rows, not selected. Some of the database types can return row count number on select too, but you can't truly be sure, if you admit that in some point you could change database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;System is built on static classes, so you can access for example router class from everywhere. I can't find reason why you should initialize router class twice. Anyway you can choose your own methods how to handle rest of the code;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It can handle javascript trough php for example for some language handling in javascript. Have to think about this more seriously, because sometimes you need to provide some other stuff to javascript;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is really fast, at least I would like to think it is. :) I am looking forward how to test this correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Almost every site I have build I needed more that one language and some sort of administration. So I also have some ideas about these two.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of things to do for framework it self, including bug tracker, forum, documentation, examples, etc. Fortunately I can't promise when exactly will be first releases, but I'm working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have some nice ideas what would be useful to have in php framework, please feel free to cantact &lt;a href="mailto:gm@mstuff.org"&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Help Latvia</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/help-latvia.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-07T06:44:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-07T06:44:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-07:/en/help-latvia.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So there it is - &lt;a href="http://helplatvia.lv"&gt;http://helplatvia.lv&lt;/a&gt; . I have been working for some while on this project after watching interview in bloomberg television (wee all now what interview). Still there are some improvements to make. As everybody knows, I'm not a designer, so don't blame me for the look of the site, but suggestions are more than welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't put big hopes for the site, this mainly is just for the framework to evolve. And I have some pretty nice ideas to make it little different from all frameworks. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Little shinny day</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/little-shinny-day.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-06T13:24:00+02:00</published><updated>2009-01-06T13:24:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2009-01-06:/en/little-shinny-day.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;And my new 50 mm F/1.8 is finally here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the tough one - buy it or not. From one side spending money on something like lenses could be the last thing to do, but from other side long time has passed when I bought camera and long time I have wanted new lenses and this one was quite cheep. I guess I will see if this was a good or bad purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this thinking about buying stuff I want and I like leaded me to a decision. Finally and officially I can say, that I am looking for an abroad job. And I mean like taking my stuff and leaving without any thinking. Problem is finding a job or I could say: "the job". Fortunately I can't think my self coding sites for clients. I want to do something new, something challenging, something interesting. For example, Mozilla corporation looks very promising, where, btw, I did send my application, but without any luck for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is for now. Little later, I will post some more information …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;And my new 50 mm F/1.8 is finally here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the tough one - buy it or not. From one side spending money on something like lenses could be the last thing to do, but from other side long time has passed when I bought camera and long time I have wanted new lenses and this one was quite cheep. I guess I will see if this was a good or bad purchase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this thinking about buying stuff I want and I like leaded me to a decision. Finally and officially I can say, that I am looking for an abroad job. And I mean like taking my stuff and leaving without any thinking. Problem is finding a job or I could say: "the job". Fortunately I can't think my self coding sites for clients. I want to do something new, something challenging, something interesting. For example, Mozilla corporation looks very promising, where, btw, I did send my application, but without any luck for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is for now. Little later, I will post some more information about positions i am seeking, CV, job I would love and places I want to go and some other cool stuff too. :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry><entry><title>Youtube embeds considered illegal in Latvia! Wtf?</title><link href="https://gm.lv/en/youtube-embeds-considered-illegal-in-latvia-wtf.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2008-01-17T19:28:00+02:00</published><updated>2008-01-17T19:28:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Gints Murāns</name></author><id>tag:gm.lv,2008-01-17:/en/youtube-embeds-considered-illegal-in-latvia-wtf.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://ukucis.com/2009/03/18/youtube-embeds-considered-illegal-in-latvia/"&gt;Read rest of the story here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Sākums"></category><category term="2009"></category></entry></feed>